Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series VII. U.S. Attorney for Western Pennsylvania
1969-1975
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.07
17.5 Linear Feet
Dick Thornburgh was sworn in as the United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania on June 4, 1969. Fighting organized crime was Thornburgh's top priority from the outset and he set forth plans for stepped-up antiracketeering efforts, including the use of a special strike force. One high profile case handled under Thornburgh's tenure was the case of official corruption of Pittsburgh District Attorney Robert Duggan. Other major cases included names such as Grosso, Mazzei, Hilton, Ferraro, Iannelli, Ferrone, La Rocca, Torquato and Bruno. Other major topics covered in the files include illegal drug traffic, civil rights/police brutality cases, and environmental litigation. The files are arranged in twelve sections: Speeches; News Releases; Public Statements; Events; Correspondence; USA Thornburgh's Files; Memoranda; Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee; Strike Forces Subcommittee of the Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee; Subcommittees of the Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee; USA Office Cases; and Issue References. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Informatioin
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Politics; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Pollution -- Law and legislation; Factory and trade waste -- Environmental aspects; Political corruption -- United States; Political corruption -- Pennsylvania; Money laundering; Drug traffic; Drug control; Organized crime -- United States; White collar crimes -- United States; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Environment; Personal papers; Government; American Bar Association; United States. Refuse Act of 1899; United States. Organized Crime Control Act of 1970; United States. Attorney (Pennsylvania: Western District); Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Thornburgh, Dick
- United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania, 1969-1975; VII.
  Scope and Contents note
  Richard Thornburgh was sworn in as the United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania on June 4, 1969. "Marking, as it did, my first ascendance to full-time public office, the ceremony was particularly memorable for me and I felt a special sense of awe in swearing to 'uphold the Constitution of the United States against all enemies, foreign and domestic,' a challenge that was to prove worthy of my every effort over the next six years" ("Evidence" draft, p. 145).
  Coincidentally the Pennsylvania Crime Commission released a major report on organized crime in the Commonwealth the very day Thornburgh's appointment was announced, thus making fighting organized crime Thornburgh's top priority from the outset. Organized crime was deeply entrenched in many facets of Western Pennsylvania business and politics including $4-6 million said to be paid illegally to Allegheny County law enforcement officials. Thornburgh "set forth plans for stepped-up antiracketeering efforts, including better coordination and cooperation among federal, state and local agencies, as well as the use of a special strike force to concentrate federal efforts" (Evidence, p. 41). "By the time I left office in mid-1975, we had mounted an unprecedented effort against corruption at the federal, state and local levels" (Evidence, p. 48).
  Among the high profile cases handled under Thornburgh tenure was the case of official corruption of Pittsburgh District Attorney Robert Duggan, who ultimately took his own life rather than face prosecution. Other major cases included names such as Grosso, Mazzei, Hilton, Ferraro, Iannelli, Ferrone, La Rocca, Torquato and Bruno. In addition to racketeering and public corruption, the illegal drug traffic issue was a major target as were civil rights/police brutality cases and environmental litigation. "These public corruption cases were a high priority for the office and for me personally as I felt that betrayal of the public trust was so subversive of our democratic processes. I was equally proud that Democrats and Republicans alike were, if corrupt, pursued with equal vigor, as we sought in all cases to truly 'follow the evidence wherever it leads'" ("Evidence" draft, p. 195).
  Public recognition of Thornburgh's success as U.S. Attorney was evidenced by the Pittsburgh Post Gazette's article entitled "Silver Knight of Area Law Enforcement." This and other such favorable publicity about Thornburgh's prosecution of corruption and racketeering cases, in particular, led to his appointment in March 1975, as Assistant Attorney General and head of the Criminal Division in Washington, an opportunity he could not pass up. "The six years I spent in the U.S. Attorney's office had not only developed my professional lawyering skills, but had given me new insights into the challenges of public management ... [and were] the happiest of my professional life" (Evidence, p. 60, and 219).
  The files are arranged in twelve sections: "Speeches," "News Releases," "Public Statements," "Events," "Correspondence," "USA Thornburgh's Files," "Memoranda," "Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee," "Strike Forces Subcommittee of the Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee," "Subcommittees of the Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee," "USA Office Cases," and "Issue References."
  - Speeches, 1.
    Speeches, available online, are arranged chronologically and titles include: speech title (when designated), group or event to which it was delivered, and location. Thornburgh delivered these U.S. Attorney speeches at various professional, political, and community occasions. Related information will be found here in "Events." The speech files contain both final copies of the delivered speeches and Thornburgh's drafts, where they existed.
    - "The Continuing American Revolution," Pittsburgh Chapter of the Sons of the American Revolution, Pittsburgh, PA, September 17, 1969 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - "Are We Really Serious About the Crime Problem?" University of Pittsburgh Law Review, Pittsburgh, PA, March 19, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - "Role of the Federal Government in Drug Abuse: Research, Education and Law Enforcement," Seminar on the Drug Abuse Problem in Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, PA, May 16, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - "Metropolitan Government - Would you Repeat the Question, Please?" University of Pittsburgh's Intercollegiate Conference on Government, Pittsburgh, PA, October 22, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - "Why Worry about Gambling...?" Greater Pittsburgh Chamber of Commerce, Pittsburgh, PA, January 21, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - "The Threat of Organized Crime in Western PA," Crawford Country Bar Association, Meadville, PA, April 22, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - "Some Observations on Our System Under Stress," McKean County Bar Association Law Day, April 30, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Memorial Day Program, McKeesport, PA, May 31, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - "Today's Youth - the Not-So-Silent Majority," United Mental Health, Inc., Pittsburgh, PA, June 7, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - "One Nation...Indivisible?" New Horizons for Faith Series, Pittsburgh, PA, July 4, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - "Crime and the Business Community," Pittsburgh Chapter National Association of Accountants, Pittsburgh, PA, September 15, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - "Organized Crime and Legitimate Business," Credo Club, Pittsburgh, PA, February 22, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 12)
    - "The Criminal Justice System in Greater Pittsburgh Today," Public Forum "What About Pittsburgh?", Pittsburgh, PA, February 24, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 13)
    - "Toward a Safer Community - the Matter of Police Protection," Association of Borough Mayors of Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, PA, April 22, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - "One Nation...Indivisible?" Flag Day Observances, Oakmont and McKeesport, PA, June 18, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 15)
    - "Restoring Respect for American Institutions - Actions Speak Louder than Words," South Hills Area School Districts' Summer Conference, Seven Springs, PA, July 30, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 16)
    - "The Threat of Organized Crime in Western PA," Beaver County Boroughs Association, Monaca, PA, September 27, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 17)
    - "Responsibilities of Elected Officials Regarding Crime and Law Enforcement," Allegheny County Association of Township Officials, Sewickley, PA, October 14, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 18)
    - "Organized Crime and Legitimate Business," Beaver County Chapter National Association of Accountants, Beaver Valley, PA, November 16, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - "The Outlook for Criminal Justice in Allegheny County," Public Affairs Forum, Pittsburgh, PA, January 18, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 20)
    - "Toward a Safer Community - the Matter of Police Protection," Allegheny County Boroughs Association, Sewickley, PA, May 25, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 21)
    - "What's Left Undone...by Whom?" First Annual Conference on Police Ethics, Pittsburgh, PA, May 15, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - "The Professional Policeman," Allegheny County Police Training Academy, Allison Park, PA, June 1, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - "Some Bits and Pieces of My Mind," Sewickley Academy, Sewickley, PA, June 7, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - "One Nation...Indivisible?" Queen Aliquippa Chapter Daughters of the American Revolution, Youghiogheny Country Club, PA, June 16, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 25)
    - Hearings of the Government Study Commission City of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, October 10,1973 (Box 33, Folder 26)
    - Hearings of the Government Study Commission City of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, October 15, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 27)
    - "Integrity...the Missing Ingredient," Western PA Safety Council, Pittsburgh, PA, January 22, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 28)
    - "The Problem of the Individual in our Mass Society," Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, PA, April 16, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 29)
    - "Challenges to Our System," Pittsburgh Branch of the American Association of University Women, Pittsburgh, PA, May 11, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - "The Threat of Organized Crime in Western PA," Meadville Area Chamber of Commerce, Meadville, PA, May 16, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 31)
    - "The Professional Policeman," Allegheny County Police Training Academy, Allison Park, PA, May 24, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - "Challenges to Criminal Justice," Western PA Chapter Association of Trial Lawyers of America, Pittsburgh, PA, June 14, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 33)
    - "Why Worry about Gambling...?" Rotary Club of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, July 17, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 34)
    - "Challenges to Our System: the Crisis of Integrity," Washington County Branch of the PA Economy League, Washington, PA, October 30, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 35)
    - "Mother's Milk Gone Sour: the Problems of Political Financing," Building Owners and Managers Association of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, November 11, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 36)
    - "Picking up the Pieces," Republican Party in Allegheny County, PA, December 11, 1974 (Box 33, Folder 37)
    - "To the Graduate: a Plea for the Healthy Skeptic," LaRoche College, Pittsburgh, PA, May 11, 1975 (Box 33, Folder 38)
    - "Cash and Carry Politics: a Challenge to Our System," PA Economy League, Inc., Beaver Falls, PA, May 22, 1975 (Box 33, Folder 39)
    - "The American Dream: What Does America Have to Look Forward to?", May 26, 1975 (Box 33, Folder 40)
    - Commission on the Review of the National Policy Toward Gambling, Philadelphia, PA, May 29, 1975 (Box 33, Folder 41)
    - "The Threat of Organized Crime in Western PA "We Are all Victims" ", 1969-1975 (Box 33, Folder 42)
    - "A Meet Person Learned in the Law: Changing Priorities in the United States Attorney's Office", 1969-1975 (Box 33, Folder 43)
    - "Partisan Politics and Law Enforcement", 1969-1975 (Box 33, Folder 44)
  - News Releases, 2.
    The releases are arranged chronologically and titles consist of a brief summary of the content of the news release. They pertain to subjects such as: organized crime and racketeering, official corruption, fraud, tax evasion and embezzlement. Releases also cover announcements concerning the actions of the Strike Forces on organized crime, narcotics and dangerous drugs, and gambling. "News Releases" and "Public Statements" were issued separately by the Office of the U.S. Attorney of Western Pennsylvania, and all are available here online. "Public Statements," in contrast to "News Releases," pertain less to specific cases but more generally to policies, and issues.
    - July 1-December 6, 1969 (Box 33, Folder 45)
      - Thornburgh was sworn in this month as United States Attorney for the Western District of PA, July 1, 1969; 1.
      - FBI agents in Pittsburgh arrested five individuals identified as leading figures in La Cosa Nostra, August 25, 1969; 2.
      - Thornburgh announced the appointment of Bernhard Schaffler as an Assistant Attorney for the Western District of PA, August, 1969; 3.
      - Thornburgh announced the retention of three Assistant U.S. Attorneys who had served under previous administrations, September 19, 1969; 4.
      - Thornburgh and H. Alan Long, District Director of the Internal Revenue Service, announced the arrest of three people accused of operating as "10 Percenters", September - December, 1969; 5.
      - Thornburgh outlined present and proposed federal weapons in the fight against organized crime, November 18, 1969; 6.
      - Thornburgh will serve as moderator of a "Workshop on Organized Crime" in the Crusade Against Crime program, December 2, 1969; 7.
      - Thornburgh announced the creation of a special Organized Crime and Racketeering Unit, December 6, 1969; 8.
    - January-July, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 46)
      - "Ready for the Seventies" is how Thornburgh describes the Federal Prosecutor's Office on the eve of the Winter Criminal Trial term, January, 1970; 1.
      - Thornburgh announced the initiation of discussions with federal officials in West Virginia concerning organized crime activities, January 22, 1970; 2.
      - Thornburgh reports that "Operation Expedite" on draft evasion cases being prosecuted in his office is getting results, February 14, 1970; 3.
      - Thornburgh will be the featured speaker at the annual banquet of the University of Pittsburgh Law Review on March 19, 1970, March, 1970; 4.
      - A federal grand jury indicted two men on charges under the 1968 Federal Extortionate Credit Transactions Act, March 31, 1970; 5.
      - Mayor Flaherty has chosen wisely in selecting John Bingler as Pittsburgh's new Public Safety Director, April 1, 1970; 6.
      - A federal grand jury indicted a Pittsburgh man on charges of theft from various employee benefit plans maintained by the Teamsters, Carpenters, Laborers and Operating Engineers Unions, April 1, 1970; 7.
      - Thornburgh announced the arrest by FBI agents of Thomas Nee, Jr. on charges of illegal interception of wire communications, April 9, 1970; 8.
      - Thornburgh will be the featured speaker at an Earth Day program at the Ellis School\, Pittsburgh on April 22, April, 1970; 9.
      - The U.S. Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit took action in two cases involving major narcotics traffickers in Pittsburgh, April 30, 1970; 10.
      - Arthur Petrosky was convicted by a federal court jury on charges of transporting illegal football pools in interstate commerce, May 5, 1970; 11.
      - Thornburgh criticized efforts of local justices of the peace to overturn the ban on jaypees holding public and political office during their terms, May 16, 1970; 12.
      - Special agents of the Federal Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs raided a suburban Pittsburgh laboratory used to manufacture amphetamines, May 20, 1970; 13.
      - A federal appeals court has dismissed as moot Allegheny County District Attorney Robert W. Duggan's appeal, May, 1970; 14.
      - There has been an increase in the number of incidents of attempted tampering or intimidation of jury members and witnesses in federal criminal cases, May, 1970; 15.
      - Thornburgh will be among nearly 100 top federal law enforcement officials meeting in D.C. for a special conference called by the Department of Justice, June 9, 1970; 16.
      - Thornburgh was promised a federal anti-organized crime Strike Force would be operative in Western PA before the end of the summer, June, 1970; 17.
      - Thornburgh called attention to federal laws which make it illegal for corporations and labor organizations to contribute to federal election campaigns, June 24, 1970; 18.
      - Ceremonies will be held in the U.S. Court for Western PA commemorating the 100th anniversary of the U.S. Department of Justice, June 30, 1970; 19.
      - Two Pittsburgh retailers entered pleas of guilty to specific charges of their respective indictments, July, 1970; 20.
      - One of the major heroin traffickers in Western PA was arrested by agents of the Federal Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs, July 16, 1970; 21.
      - Thornburgh announced the appointment of David M. Curry as an Assistant United States Attorney for the Western District of PA, July 20, 1970; 22.
      - The Department of Justice wishes to make it clear it will tolerate no attempts on the part of criminals to threaten Judges, July 24, 1970; 23.
      - Assistant U.S. Attorney Douglas D. McBroom urged police officers to exercise discretion when dealing with hard narcotics users, July 30, 1970; 24.
    - July-December, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Thornburgh announced revised assignments within his office in preparation for increased federal anti-organized crime activity, August, 1970; 1.
      - A number of persons, including several Allegheny County Detectives, have been subpoenaed to appear before a federal grand jury this week in Pittsburgh, August, 1970; 2.
      - A federal grand jury indicted the President and Secretary-Treasurer of District 5 of the United Mine Workers of America on charges filing false financial reports, August 4, 1970; 3.
      - U.S. Customs agents seized more than a quarter of a pound of raw opium shortly after its delivery through the U.S. mail, August 5, 1970; 4.
      - The federal grand jury investigating Samuel Ferraro on tax obstruction recessed late this morning, August 13, 1970; 5.
      - A federal grand jury returned a fifteen-count indictment against Auldus Turner, Jr. and Joseph Schuchert, Jr., August 26, 1970; 6.
      - A federal grand jury returned a two-count indictment against Reuben Lando for failing to keep accurate records of amphetamine and barbiturates sales, September 11, 1970; 7.
      - Joseph Harper was sentenced to one year in prison for willful failure to file Federal Income Tax returns, September 25, 1970; 8.
      - Thornburgh announced that Assistant U.S. Attorney Douglas D. McBroom had accepted a position on the staff of U.S. Attorney Stan G. Pitkin in Seattle, October 4, 1970; 9.
      - Thornburgh will be the featured speaker at the annual "Rigatoni Night" of the Glassport, PA, Lion's Club, October 13, 1970; 10.
      - Robert Torquato was sentenced to four years in prison for jury tampering, October 14, 1970; 11.
      - A federal grand jury indicted a McKeesport City Councilman on illegal wire-tapping charges under the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968, October 14, 1970; 12.
      - Thornburgh reminded corporations and labor organizations that federal laws make it illegal for them to contribute to federal election campaigns, October 16, 1970; 13.
      - PA Governor Raymond P. Shafer will host "The Governor and the People" to be shown locally, October 24, 1970; 14.
      - Public statements that a narcotics addict was denied help by every public agency or hospital approached for aid are untrue, October 28, 1970; 15.
      - Federal authorities took court action to force disclosures of certain financial affairs of John Sebastian LaRocca, November 5, 1970; 16.
      - Thornburgh filed criminal charges against Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation for alleged unlawful discharge of oil\, grease and metallic particles into the Ohio River, November 9, 1970; 17.
      - Thornburgh characterized community hypocrisy as a major stumbling block in dealing with rehabilitating narcotics addicts, November 14, 1970; 18.
      - A federal grand jury returned a 21 count indictment charging misapplication of funds of Mellon National Bank and Western PA National Bank, November 17, 1970; 19.
      - Over 100 FBI agents staged a series of coordinated raids on 22 suspected gambling locations in the Pittsburgh area, November 21, 1970; 20.
      - A federal grand jury indicted six area men on charges connected with the alleged theft of a tractor-trailer load of color televisions, December 8, 1970; 21.
      - Thornburgh will commence a probe into large scale illegal gambling operations in Pittsburgh, December 8, 1970; 22.
      - Thornburgh announced the appointment of the first female Assistant U.S. Attorney to serve in his office. The appointee is Kathleen Kelly, December 13, 1970; 23.
      - Indictments are the first results of a year-long investigations by FBI agents into organized illegal sports betting in the Pittsburgh area, December, 1970; 24.
      - Federal anti-crime efforts in Western PA will be stepped up considerably during 1971 due to a doubling of available prosecutors, December 30, 1970; 25.
    - January-June, 1971 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Federal authorities took further court action to force disclosure of the financial affairs of John Sebastian LaRocca, January 4, 1971; 1.
      - A former detective on the Allegheny County Racket Squad was convicted of two counts of perjury, January 13, 1971; 2.
      - Statement of Thornburgh before the Special Committee on Alcoholism and Narcotics of the Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, January 18, 1971; 3.
      - Thornburgh and members of his staff have scheduled a number of meetings with student groups on local campuses to open better lines of communication, January 22, 1971; 4.
      - A special federal grand jury to investigate organized crime in Western PA will begin receiving testimony, January 23, 1971; 5.
      - Additional suspected illegal wiretaps are under investigation by federal officials in the Pittsburgh area, February 16, 1971; 6.
      - The conviction of Augustine Ferrone was upheld today, February 19, 1971; 7.
      - Allegheny County's criminal justice system requires a massive overhaul, February 20, 1971; 8.
      - Four members of Local 341 of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters were indicted for criminal violations of the Hobbs Anti-Racketeering Act, March 11, 1971; 9.
      - A federal grand jury indicted Alphonso Monzo for violations of the Fair Labor Standards Act, March 17, 1971; 10.
      - Judge Louis Rosenberg has ordered the production of books and records of North Star Cement Block Company\, Inc. to be made to the IRS, March 24, 1971; 11.
      - A special federal grand jury returned two indictments against a total of 26 persons alleged to be involved in two illegal numbers and sports-betting operations, March 26, 1971; 12.
      - Judge Joseph F. Weis refused to appoint a lawyer at taxpayers' expense for Frank X. Gaca, March 31, 1971; 13.
      - Thornburgh instituted criminal proceedings under the Refuse Act against the U.S. Steel Corporation, Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation, and the Wheeling-Pittsburgh Steel Corporation, April 6, 1971; 14.